Guide to the Riggs Family records (Page R. Bradley donation), 1800-1950 MS2336
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Riggs Family records (Page R. Bradley donation)
1800-1950
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Bradley, Page Riggs
MS2336
7.25 Linear Feet Collection contains 2 record center boxes, 4 flat boxes, and 1 slim document box.
This collection contains materials relating to the Riggs family, a prominent family in the Washington, D.C. area notable for its banking fame. The materials in this collection include business ledgers, correspondence, and personal belongings related to various members of the Riggs family. These materials date from the early 1800s to 1950. The most notable members of the Riggs family represented in this collection are: Elisha Riggs (New York merchant & Georgetown business man), George Washington Riggs (head of Riggs' banking business, known as "The President's Banker"), Elisha Francis Riggs (successor to G.W. Riggs in banking firm), Thomas Riggs, Jr. (Governor of Alaska Territory & U.S. Commissioner to the International Boundary Commission), and Thomas Lawrason Riggs (first Catholic chaplain of Yale University & musical theatre lyricist).
Biographical / Historical
The Riggs family, notable for its banking fame, was prominent in the Washington, D.C. area in the 19th and 20th century. The earliest incarnation of Riggs Bank was formed in 1836 when William Wilson Corcoran opened a small brokerage house. In 1840, Corcoran and George Washington Riggs, the son of a neighbor, formed "Corcoran & Riggs", which offered checking and depositing services. The bank got a major boost in 1844, when The U.S. government assigned Corcoran & Riggs to be the only federal depository in Washington. In 1854 Corcoran retired, and the bank changed its name to "Riggs & Co." After accepting a government charter, "Riggs National Bank" was born in 1896. By 1900, Riggs was twice as large as any other bank in D.C. It embarked on a successful project to become known as the bank of embassies and diplomats, and by 1950 most embassies in Washington were customers. Many branches thereafter opened within embassies in Washington D.C. and London. Riggs Bank was bought by PNC for $779 million in 2005.
The most notable members of the Riggs family represented in this collection are: Elisha Riggs (New York merchant & Georgetown business man), George Washington Riggs (head of Riggs' banking business, known as "The President's Banker"), Elisha Francis Riggs (successor to G.W. Riggs in banking firm), Thomas Riggs, Jr. (Governor of Alaska Territory & U.S. Commissioner to the International Boundary Commission), and Thomas Lawrason Riggs (first Catholic chaplain of Yale University & musical theatre lyricist).
Scope and Contents
Materials in this collection include business ledgers, correspondence, and personal belongings related to various members of the Riggs family. These materials date from the early 1800s to 1950.
Arrangement
Organized into 3 series: Business ledgers, Correspondence, and Personal artifacts.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Page R. Bradley, 9 March 2015 [2015.019]
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Washington (D.C.); Banks and banking -- Washington (D.C.); New York (N.Y.); Banks and banking; Banks and banking -- United States; Bradley, Page Riggs; Riggs family; Riggs, Elisha Francis; Riggs, Elisha; Riggs and Co.; Riggs National Bank; Riggs, Elisha; Riggs, George Washington; Riggs, Thomas; Riggs, T. Lawrason (Thomas Lawrason); Riggs, Samuel; Corcoran, W. W. (William Wilson); Peabody, Riggs & Co.; Riggs & Co. of New York; Riggs & Levering; Riggs, Peabody & Co.; Riggs, Medora; Riggs, Lawrason; Corcoran & Riggs
- Business ledgers, 1826-1851; Series 1
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains 3 business ledgers dating from 1826 to 1851. The material relates to the businesses of the Riggs family, including Riggs and Levering and Elisha Riggs & Sons. Material also includes estate records of Samuel Lukens.
  - Ledger/account book (Estate - Samuel Lukens), 1826-1836; Series 1; 26 pages with text and 12 additional pages showing text cut out. No company name identified. "ESTATE" imprinted on cover. "Sam'l Lukens" written on front and inside cover. (1/4 leather, quarto). Fragile and worn from age and use. (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Ledger/receipt book for Elisha Riggs and Sons, St. Louis and New York, 1840-1842; Series 1; 125 pages including 3 pages of index. (Full leather, quarto). Fragile and worn from age and use. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Ledger/receipt book for Riggs and Levering, New York City, 1846-1851; Series 1; 350 pages containing 12 pages of an alphabetical index and 340 pages of text entries. (1/4 leather, quarto). Fragile and worn from age and use. (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1826-1939; Series 2
  This series consists of correspondence with the Riggs family. This material dates from 1826 to 1939. Writers and recipients include: Elisha Riggs, Thomas Riggs, Medora Riggs, Mary R.L. McCullough, A. Bowie Davis, George W. Howard, and George Dewey.
  - Letter: Elisha Riggs to brother Thomas Riggs, 1826 March 5; Series 2; 6 pages (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - Letter: A. Bowie Davis to George W. Howard, 1887 March 28; Series 2; 6 pages; regarding the life of the late Elisha Riggs (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Letter: George Dewey to Mrs. Medora Riggs, 1914 January 6; Series 2; 1 page; on Admiral of the Navy stationary (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Letter: Mary R.L. McCullough to Thomas Riggs, 1939 October 11; Series 2; 2 pages (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Letter: Mary R.L. McCullough to Thomas Riggs, 1939 October 23; Series 2; 2 and 1/2 pages (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Letter: Mary R.L. McCullough to Thomas Riggs, 1939 November 14; Series 2; 2 pages (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Personal artifacts, Circa 1800 to Circa 1950; Series 3
  This series consists of various items belonging to members of the Riggs family. Personalized objects include: sheet music, daguerreotypes, fine china, serving dishes, miniature paintings, cuff links, dress pins, card cases, hair ornaments, shoe ornaments, napkin rings, lapel pins, medallions, pendants, buttoniers, cigarette cases, office supplies, a whistle pendant, a ceramic fish, and a woodblock stamp. The objects range in date from the mid-1800s to 1950. Owners of the objects include: Thomas Lawrason Riggs, C.F. Riggs, Elisha Francis Riggs, B.F. Riggs, F.E. Riggs, F.L. Riggs, H. Riggs, Lawrason Riggs, Miss J.R. Shedden, Amelia J. Riggs, George Washington Riggs, Samuel J. Riggs, Mary Ann (Karrick) Riggs, Joseph Riggs, and Karrick Riggs.
  Arranged alphabetically.
  - 19th century napkin ring, Circa 1800s; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    General Physical Description note
    19th century sterling silver napkin ring.
  - American Legion buttonier, undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    American Legion buttonier from B.F. Riggs' jewelry box.
    Man's wooden jewelry box, with remnants of dried black leather on wood; "B.F. Riggs" engraved on lid; contained 7 buttoniers, small ceramic fish, empty pencil case, empty leather bag, 14 carat fraternity pin (1"L x 5/8"W) engraved on back "T.L. Riggs," a gold pendant with image of Moliere on front and "L. Riggs" engraved on back, and Yale Drama pendant with "T.L. Riggs" engraved on back
  - B.F. Riggs' jewelry box: documentation, undated; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    Documentation about the Man's Jewelry Box. The box itself was in poor shape due to age and insect damage, therefore it was not saved. The contents were removed and cataloged individually.
  - Bakelite hair comb, undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    Bakelite comb hair ornament with silver, clear stones and pearls (4.5" x 3")
  - Bakelite hairpin (1 of 2), undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    One of two Bakelite hairpins with silver and clear stones (4"L)
  - Bakelite hairpin (2 of 2), undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Brass writing pen holder, Circa 1800s; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    19th century engraved brass writing pen holder
  - Ceramic fish, undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Off-white ceramic fish. From B.F. Riggs' jewelry box.
  - C.F. Riggs' alligator hide flask case, undated; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    Brown alligator hide flask case with sterling silver trim and "CFR" monogram. Found inside F.E. Riggs' leather grooming kit.
    Man's leather grooming kit; "F.E. Riggs London 1867" engraved on lid of box; kit contained chamois nail buffer in wood sheath, wood brush with boar bristles, six glass containers with silverplate lids (one lid mising), shaving brush in ivory-colored case, alligator hide flask case with sterling silver trim and silver "CFR" monogram
  - Daguerreotype of Joseph Riggs, 1852; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 18)
    Daguerreotype of Joseph Riggs in larger decorative rectangular case, dated 1852
  - Daguerreotype of Joseph Riggs, Circa 1852; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    Daguerreotype of Joseph Riggs in smaller fabric oval case
  - Daguerreotype of Karrick Riggs, undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    Daguerreotype of Karrick Riggs in smaller decorative rectangular case
  - Decorative buttoniers (Set of 3), undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    Set of three decorative buttoniers with turquoise details. From B.F. Riggs' Jewelry Box.
  - Decorative buttoniers (Set of 3), undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Decorative pins (4), Circa 1800s; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    19th century decorative dress/coat pins.
  - Elisha Francis Riggs' woodblock stamp, undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 19)
    Woodblock stamp with "RECTE AGE NIL TIME E.F. RIGGS" and dog carrying arrow; (2" x 2")
  - Engraved silverplate tray belonging to Miss J.R. Shedden, 1853 July 22; Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Silver Plate Tray (18.5" x 15"); Engraved "Miss J R Shedden from the Pupils of the "Hive" Natchez July 22, 1853"
  - F.E. Riggs' leather grooming kit: chamois nail buffer with case, Circa 1867; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - F.E. Riggs' leather grooming kit: documentation, Circa 1867; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    General note
    Documentation about the Man's Leather Grooming Kit. The box itself was in poor shape due to age and insect damage, therefore it was not saved. The contents were removed and cataloged individually.
  - F.E. Riggs' leather grooming kit: glass oval container with lid, Circa 1867; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - F.E. Riggs' leather grooming kit: glass tube (no lid), Circa 1867; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - F.E. Riggs' leather grooming kit: glass tube with lid, Circa 1867; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - F.E. Riggs' leather grooming kit: shaving brush, Circa 1867; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - F.E. Riggs' leather grooming kit: small glass container with lid, Circa 1867; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - F.E. Riggs' leather grooming kit: small glass container with lid, Circa 1867; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - F.E. Riggs' leather grooming kit: small glass tube with lid, Circa 1867; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - F.E. Riggs' leather grooming kit: wood brush with boar bristles, Circa 1867; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - F.L. Riggs' whistle pendant, undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    Sterling silver whistle pendant engraved "FLR". (1.25"L; weight 4.7g)
  - Fine china tea set: creamer, undated; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    8 piece porcelain fine china tea set with Riggs coat of arms. No maker marks. 2 teacups are damaged.
  - Fine china tea set: lidded sugar bowl, undated; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Fine china tea set: teacup, undated; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Fine china tea set: teacup, undated; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Fine china tea set: teacup, undated; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Fine china tea set: teacup (damaged), undated; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    Damaged: chipped 8 piece porcelain fine china tea set with Riggs coat of arms. No maker marks. 2 teacups are damaged.
  - Fine china tea set: teacup (damaged), undated; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    Damaged: Broken handle 8 piece porcelain fine china tea set with Riggs coat of arms. No maker marks. 2 teacups are damaged.
  - Fine china tea set: teapot, undated; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Glass cigarette humidor, undated; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    Oval glass cigarette humidor with sterling silver lid; dog carrying arrow engraved on lid; A. Barrett & Sons, Piccadilly 157 & 158
  - H. Riggs' glass inkwell, 1950; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    Glass inkwell; 1950; sterling silver hinged lid with "HR" monogram engraved
  - Ivory card holder, undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Ivory hinged accordion card holder with silver pencil and silver monogram on front (3"W x 4"L)
  - Karrick Van Zandt Riggs' personalized beer stein lid, 1873; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    Personalized beer stein lid made of silver metal and ceramic. Metal handle has small figure of bearded man with a pint. Ceramic inlay has colored image of dogs carrying arrows and the phrase "RECTE AGE NIL TIME." Printed on the reverse side of ceramic inlay: Karrick Van Zandt [/] Riggs [/] Hannover 1873" Ceramic is cracked in two places.
  - Lawrason Riggs' jewelry box: documentation, undated; Series 3 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    Man's jewelry box; 7"L x 4"W x 3"H; red leather; "L.R." embossed in gold on hinged lid; contained six small medallions each less than an inch long and one small lapel pin
  - Lawrason Riggs' Moliere Pendant, undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Moliere pendant with "L. Riggs" engraved on back. From B.F. Riggs' jewelry box.
  - Lapel pin, undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    Lapel pin. From L. Riggs' jewelry box.
  - Parlor sheet music belonging to Amelia J. Riggs, Mid 1800s; Series 3 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    Bound Collection os sheet music. "Amelia J. Riggs" imprinted on cover. (1/4 leather, quarto). Fragile and worn from age and use.
  - Religious medallions (2), undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Two religious medallions, likely belonging to T.L. Riggs. From L. Riggs' jewelry box.
  - Religious medallions (4), undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    Four religious medallions on metal loop, likely belonging to T.L. Riggs. From L. Riggs' jewelry box.
  - Salt/pepper shaker, undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    Silverplate salt or pepper shaker with lid and handle (Bachmann Guernsey)
  - Shoe ornament (1 of 2), undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    One of two shoe ornaments, silver metal with clear stones (2.5"L x 1.25"W)
  - Shoe ornament (2 of 2), undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Silver metal cup belonging to George Washington Riggs, undated; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    Engraved: "GWR [/] 22"
  - Silver salt cellar, undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 16)
    Three-footed sterling silver salt cellar; (2.5"D); lion passant, leopard face, capital Times Roman "E F"; two other very worn marks; weight 55.7g
  - Silverplate business card case, undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 20)
    Silverplate business/calling card case with hinged opening at end, floral pattern, and central engraving (3 3/4"L)
  - Silverplate cigarette case with cover, undated; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    Silverplate cigarette case; Galt & Bro., Washington, D.C.; "RECTE AGE NIL TIME" engraved under image of a dog carrying an arrow; fabric protective cover
  - Silverplate rectangular-footed tray, undated; Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    Silverplate rectangular-footed tray with two handles; "RECTE AGE NIL TIME" engraved under a dog carrying an arrow; FHCS Co. (29"L x 17.5"W)
  - Silverplate round-footed tray, undated; Series 3 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    Silverplate round-footed tray; (20"D); dog carrying arrow engraved in the center
  - Sterling silver creamer, undated; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Sterling silver creamer, repousse; "Starr & Marcus English Sterling No. 364" stamped over "New York 449"; 3 inches H; illegible monogram (possibly MS) engraved; weight 158.3g
  - Sterling silver lidded sugar bowl, undated; Series 3 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    Sterling silver double handled and lidded sugar bowl, repousse; "Starr & Marcus English Sterling No. 364" stamped over "New York 449"; 3 inches H; illegible monogram (possibly MS) engraved; weight 257.4g
  - Sterling silver pitcher, undated; Series 3 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    Sterling silver pitcher; marks: D&J over W; lion passant, leopard face; Times Roman capital P; 5.5 inches H; engraved "RECITE AGE NIL TIME" on a belt encircling a dog with an arrow in its mouth; weight 428.6g
  - Thomas Lawrason Riggs' fraternity pin, undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Fraternity pin with "T.L. Riggs" engraved on back. (1"L x 5/8"W). From B.F. Riggs' jewelry box.
  - Thomas Lawrason Riggs' personalized cuff links, undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    Pair of engraved initialed cuff links belonging to Thomas Lawrason Riggs.
  - Thomas Lawrason Riggs' personalized napkin ring, undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Silverplate napkin ring engraved "TLR"
  - Thomas Lawrason Riggs' Yale drama pendant, undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Yale Drama pendant with "T.L. Riggs" engraved on back. From B.F. Riggs' jewelry box.
  - Watercolor miniature painting of Mary Ann (Karrick) Riggs, undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    Size: 1 3/4" x 1 1/2"
    Note on box: Top of Box: Mrs Riggs [/] Miniature Bottom of Box: nee Karrick [/] Mrs Riggs [/] miniature [/] K's g-mother
    Note on envelope: Miniature of Mary Ann (Karrick) Riggs, [/] 20, wife of Elisha Riggs of NYC - by unknown [/] artist - from the effects of her great gradson, [/] Pontius(?) (Riggs) Hayes - given to me by Henry [/] de Godfrey in NYC - who hid it(?) from Pauline's [/] executor Keith Kane - [/] JB Riggs
  - Watercolor miniature painting of Samuel J. Riggs, undated; Series 3 (Box 3, Folder 23)
    Note on Envelope:
    Miniature of Samuel J. Riggs [/] (1811-1847) [/] son of Romulus and Mercy Ann [/] (Lawrason) Riggs of Philadelphia. [/] Painted in Paris in 1833. This picture [/] was damaged by Samuel Kirk & Son of Balt(imore) in [/] forcing it into frame, cracked across the face - for which I made them pay me $500.00
    Size: 1 1/2" x 1 1/4" Painting is in gold, oval frame with a red ribbon tied to the top.